Welcome to the Course First up thanks for joining.
I am super excited to show you everything that Noad can do.
I packed this course with a ton of content projects challenges and real world examples all designed
to teach you know by doing this means you'll be getting your hands dirty early on in the next section.
Writing some code and you're going to be writing code for every project this is not one of those copy
and paste courses you'll be writing every line of code that powers our applications.
Now all of these projects are a ton of fun to build and they were designed to teach you everything required
to launch your own node app from planning to development and testing to deploying.
Now as you do launch these applications and move through the course you are going to run into errors.
It's just going to happen.
Maybe something doesn't install as expected.
Or maybe you try to run an app and instead of getting the expected output you get a really long obscure
error message.
Either way I am here to help.
At the bottom of every video you can find a link called Q&amp;A.
This is going to link you to the Q and A section for that video.
You'll be able to find other questions asked by other students and you'll be able to ask your own question.
So if you get stuck post there and I'll get back to you right away.
Let's go ahead and dive into the first section.
Well you'll learn what note is why it's useful and you're going to write your first app.
That's coming up next.
So let's get to it.