Hello and welcome to Section 2 getting set up in this section you're going to get your local environment
set up for the rest of the course whether you're on OSX Linux or Windows will be installing node and
looking at exactly how we can run node applications.
We're going to talk about what node is and why you'd ever want to use it why you would want to use no.
As opposed to something like Rails C++ Java or any other language that can accomplish similar tasks.
At the end you will be running your very first node application.
It's going to be simple but it is going to get us down that path towards creating real world production
node apps which is the end goal of this course.
Let's dive right in.
Installing node