It before we started talking about what note is and why it's useful.
Which I'm sure you are wondering.
We're going to go ahead and install node on your machine because in the next couple of videos as I aim
to answer those questions we're going to want to run a little bit of node code now to get started in
this video we just need two programs a browser.
I'm going to be using Chrome throughout the course but any browser will do.
And in the terminal sometimes known as the command line on Linux or the command prompt on Windows.
Let's go ahead and open that up right now.
I'm going to use Spotlight to open up the terminal which is what it's known as on my operating system.
If you're on Windows look for something like the command prompt you can search using the Windows key
and then by typing.
And on Linux you're looking for something called the command line.
Although depending on your distribution it might be called the terminal or command prompt.
Now once you have that program open you're going to see something a little daunting.
It's a screen.
Yours probably has a black background with white text.
And essentially it's waiting for you to run a command.
We're going to be running quite a few commands from the terminal throughout the course and then around
four or five videos.
I'm going to give you a crash course.
So if you've never used this before you can start navigating comfortably.
But for now you don't need to worry about any of that.
We're not going to run any commands for the moment in the browser.
We can head over to node j ass dot org to grab the installer for the latest version of Node.
Hey this is Andrew from the future with a quick update.
As you saw on the previous screen when this course was first created node version 6 was the latest version
of node available.
As you can clearly see these days that's no longer the case.
The latest version now is version 10.
I've updated the course to support version 10 and you're going to have to actually install the 10 of
node or greater in order to work through the entire class as new node versions come out.
New features are added to the language and if you're using an older version of node you're not going
to be able to work through the class since it was updated to cover these awesome new features.
So long story short make sure you are using node the 10 as seen here or greater if you are going to
be able to move through the entire class with no problems.
All right that's it for this little interruption.
Let's get back to the regular video for now though.
All we have to do is click this button.
It downloads the installer and the installer is one of those basic click Next a few times and you're
done.
Type of installers there's no need to run any fancy commands.
I'm going to go ahead and start the installer here.
It's just going to ask me a few questions.
Go ahead and click next or continue through all of them.
You might want to specify a custom destination but if you don't know what that means and you don't usually
do it when installing programs that go ahead and skip that step to here I can see I'm using just 47
megabytes.
No problem.
I'm going to go ahead and run in the installer by entering my password and once I enter my password
it should really only take a couple of seconds to get node installed.
And here you go.
We have a message that says the installation was completed successfully which means we are good to go.
And now that node has been installed successfully we can go ahead and verify that by running it from
the terminal over inside of the terminal.
I'm going to actually shut it down by going to quit terminal and open it up again.
The reason I'm opening it up is because we've installed a new command and some terminals require a restart
before it's going to be able to run that new command.
In our case we've restarted things and we can run our brand new command.
We're going to type it out just like this node space hyphen the what we're doing here is we're running
the node command and we're passing it what's called a flag.
This is a hyphen sign followed by a letter could be a it could be J or in our case it's v.
This is going to print the version of node currently installed.
We might get an error.
Like this if you try to run a command that doesn't exist like A.D SDF you'll see.
Command not found.
If you see that it usually means the node installer didn't work correctly or you haven't ran it in the
first place.
In our case though a running node with the the flag should result in a number in our case it's version
six point two point two.
Once again make sure that you have a V-6 version of node installed.
Otherwise a lot of the videos throughout the course just aren't going to work if you do have node installed
and you're seeing something like what I see here then you are done.
I'll see you next time where we start exploring exactly what node is.
Stay tuned.
I will see you then.