In this video we're going to take a look at what node is know to came about when the original developers
took javascript.
Something you could usually only run inside of the browser and they let it run on your machine as a
standalone process.
This meant we could create applications using javascript outside of the context of the browser.
Now javascript previously had a limited feature set when I used it in the browser I could do things
like Update R-AL and remove the node logo.
Adding click events or anything else but I couldn't really do much more with KNode.
We now have a feature set that looks much more similar to other languages like Java Python or HP.
We can write node applications using the javascript syntax that manipulate your file system in creating
and removing folders.
They can query databases directly and you can even create web servers using Knode all of which will
be doing inside of course.
These were things that were not possible in the past and they are because of note.
Now both the node and the javascript that gets executed inside of your browser are both running on the
exact same engine.
It's called the V8 javascript runtime engine.
It's an open source engine that takes javascript code and compiles it into much faster machine code
and that's a big part of what makes node j ass so blazing fast.
Machine Code is low level code that your computer can run directly without needing to interpret it.
Your machine only knows how to run certain types of code.
For example your machine can't run javascript code or code without first converting it into something
it does now because the V-8 engine does this so well.
Node is just super quick.
Using this V-8 engine we can take our javascript code compile it to much quicker machine code and execute
that.
This is where all those new features come in.
The V-8 engine.
It's written in a language called C plus plus.
So if you want to extend the node language you don't write node code you write C++ code that builds
off of what V.A already has in place.
Now we're not going to be writing any C++ code in this course.
This course is not about adding on to note it is about using knode.
So we're only going to be writing a javascript code.
Speaking of javascript code let's go ahead and start writing some.
Over inside of the terminal.
Now throughout the course we're going to be creating files and executing those files.
But we can actually create a brand new node process by running the node command.
Here you see I have a little right carrot.
This is waiting for javascript node code not a new command prompt command.
That means I can run something like.
Console dot log which as you probably know log's a message to the screen.
A log is a function.
So I'm going to call it as such opening and closing my parentheses and passing in a string inside of
two single quotes a message like hello world.
This is going to print Hello World to the screen.
If I click on her hello world prints just like you'd expect.
Now what actually happened behind the scenes.
Well this is what node does.
It takes your javascript code it compiles into machine code and executes it.
Here you can see it executed our code.
Printing out Hello world.
Now this V-8 engine is running behind the scenes when we execute this command and it's also running
over inside of the Chrome browser.
If I open up the developer tools in Chrome by going to settings more tools developer tools I can ignore
most of the things I'm just looking for the console which is a tab right here.
This console is exactly like what we have over here.
It's a place where we can run some Javascript code.
I can type the exact same command console log hello world inside single quotes.
Run it and right here you can see Hello World prints to the screen which is the exact same result we
got when we ran it up above.
In both cases we're running it through the V-8 engine and in both cases the output is the same.
Now we already know that the two are different.
Node has features like file system manipulation and the browser has features like manipulating what's
shown inside of the window.
Let's take a quick moment to explore their differences inside of the browser.
You've probably used window if you've done any javascript development window as the global object it
stores basically everything you have access to.
Here you can see things like array down below we have all sorts of CSSA manipulation.
We have Google Analytics keywords.
Essentially every variable you create lives inside of window.
We have something similar inside of node.
It's not called window because there is no browser window.
It is called Global global stores a lot of the same things.
Here you can see methods that might be familiar like set time out and set interval up above.
We have most of the things that are defined over inside of window with some exceptions.
Now inside of the Chrome browser I also have access to something called Document Document stores a reference
to the DOM up above the document shows exactly what I have up here inside of the browser's viewport.
I can make changes to the document down below to update what it's showing up above.
Now obviously we don't have this HDMI document inside of node but we do have something similar.
What we have is called process.
You can view it by running process from node.
And here we have a lot of information about the specific node process that's being executed.
There's also methods available here to shut down the current node process.
What I'd like you to do is go ahead and run Process dot exit passing in as an argument.
The number is zero 0 to say that things exited without air when I run this command you can see I'm now
back at the command prompt.
I've left node and I'm at a place where I could run any regular command prompt command like checking
my node version.
I can always get back into node by running node and I can leave it without using process.
Exit by using Control C twice.
Now I'm back at my regular command prompt.
So these are the notable differences obviously inside of the browser when you have this viewable area
window gets changed to global and that document basically becomes process.
Now obviously that's a generalization but those are some of the big picture changes we'll be exploring
all the minutia throughout the course.
Now when someone on the street asks you what is Noad you can say oh node's a javascript runtime that
uses the V-8 engine and when they ask you what the V-8 engine is you can say that the engine is an open
source javascript engine written in C++ that takes javascript code and compiles it to machine code.
It's used inside of no.
Yes and it's used in the chrome browser.
That's it for this one.
We've explored the what of node in the next video we're going to explore why nodes become so popular
its advantages its disadvantages and a heck of a lot more.
So stay tuned.
I will see you then.