In this video we're going to cover the why behind it no.
Yes.
Why is it so good at creating back and apps and why is it becoming so popular with companies like Netflix
Oubre and Wal-Mart all using knode.
Yes in production as you might have noticed since you're taking this course when people want to learn
a new back and language more and more they're turning to node as that language.
They want to learn the nodes skill set is in hot demand for both front end developers who need to use
know to day to day to do things like compile their applications to engineers who are creating applications
and utilities using node.
Yes all of this has made Noad the prime choice in 2016 as the back end language of choice.
Now I've left this home page up for a reason in the last video we addressed the first sentence.
We took a look at node j us and we learned that it's built on top of the V8 javascript engine.
There's only three sentences here.
So in this video we're going to take a look at the second two.
We're going to go ahead and read them now.
Then we'll break it down.
We're learning exactly why node is so great.
The first sentence.
No genius uses an event driven non-blocking IO model that makes it lightweight and efficient.
We're going to explore all of that in just a second.
The second sentence which we'll explore at the end of the video noted Julius's package ecosystem NPM
is the largest ecosystem of open source libraries in the world.
Now these two sentences they have a ton of information packed into them.
The second sentence has a lot more Pakhtun than the third.
Well we're going to do is go over a few code examples.
We're going to dive into some charts and graphs and we'll explore what makes no different and what makes
it so great note is an event driven nonblocking language.
Now you see non-blocking IO right here.
What is I.
Oh IO is something that your application does all of the time when you're reading or writing to a database
that is I O.
Which is short for input output.
This is the communication from your node application to other things inside of the Internet of Things.
This could be a database read and write request.
You may be changing some files on your file system or maybe making an HTP request to a separate web
server such as a Google API for fetching a map for the users current location.
All of those use I O when IO takes time.
Now the non-blocking IO is great.
That means while one user is requesting a u r l from google other users can be requesting database file
read and write access.
They can be requesting all sorts of things without preventing anyone else from getting some work done.
Let's go ahead and take a look at the difference between blocking and nonblocking software development
right here.
I have two files that we're going to be executing in just a minute.
But for the moment we're going to explore how each operates the steps that are required in order for
the program to finish.
This is going to show us the big differences between blocking which I have on the left which is not
what node uses and nonblocking on the right which is exactly how all of our node applications in the
course are going to operate.
You don't have to understand the individual details like what require is in order to understand what's
going on here.
We're going to be breaking things down in a very general sense.
The first line on each is responsible for fetching a function that gets called and this function this
is going to be our simulated I O function that is going to a database fetching some user data and printing
it to the screen.
Both files do the same thing they just do it in different ways.
After we load in the function of both files try to fetch a user with an ID of one to three when it gets
that user it prints it to the screen with the user one string before and then it goes on and it fetches
the user with it.
Three two one is the I.D. It prints that to the screen.
And finally both files add up one plus.
Storing the result which is three in the some variable and printing it to the screen.
Now will they all do the same thing they do in very different ways.
Let's break down the individual steps down below.
We're going to go over what node executes and how long it takes you can consider these seconds it doesn't
really matter it's just to show the relative operating speed between the two.
The first thing that happens inside of our blocking example right here is we fetch the user on line
3.
Now this request requires us to go to a database which is an I O operation to fetch that user by ID.
This takes a little bit of time.
In our case and we're going to say it takes three seconds.
Next online for we print the user to the screen which is not an operation and it runs right away printing
user 1 to the screen.
You can see that takes almost no time at all.
Next up we go ahead and we wait on the fetching of a user to when user 2 comes back.
As you might expect we print it to the screen which is exactly what happens on line 7 right here.
Finally down below we add up our number and we print it to the screen.
None of that is I.
Oh.
So right here we have are some printing to the screen in barely any time.
This is how blocking works.
It's called the blocking because well we're fetching from the database which is an IO operation.
Our application cannot do anything else.
This means our machine sits around idle waiting for the database to respond and can't even do something
simple like adding two numbers and printing them to the screen.
It's just not possible in a blocking system on the right.
We have our nonblocking example this is how we're going to be building our node applications.
Let's go ahead and break this down line by line first up things start much the same way.
We're starting the get user function for user 1 which is exactly what we do here but we're not waiting.
We're simply kicking off that event.
This is all part of the event loop inside of know J S which is something we'll be exploring in detail.
Notice it takes a little bit of time.
We're just starting the request we're not waiting for that data.
The next thing we do might surprise you.
We're not printing user 1 to the screen because we're still waiting for that request to come back.
Instead we start the process of fetching our user with the idea of three to one.
Here we're kicking off another event which takes just a little bit of time to do.
It is not an I O operation now behind the scenes the fetching of the database is IO but starting the
event calling this function is not.
So it happens really quickly.
Next up we print the sum the sum doesn't care about either of the two user objects they're basically
unrelated.
So there's no need to wait for the users to come back before I print that some variable down below after
we print the sum.
What happens when we have this dotted box.
This is the simulated time it takes for our event to get responded to.
Now this box it is the exact same with as the box over here using nonblocking doesn't make our IO operations
any faster but what it does do is it lets us run more than one operation at the same time.
Here we start two IO operations before the half second to Mark and right here between three and three
and a half seconds both come back.
Now the result here is that the entire application finishes much quicker.
The nonblocking version finished in just over three seconds while the blocking version takes just over
six.
A difference of 50 percent and that 50 percent comes from the fact that here we have two requests each
taking three seconds and here we have two requests each taking three seconds.
But they run at the same time using the nonblocking model.
We can still do stuff like printing the sum without having to wait for our database to respond.
Now this is the big difference between the two.
Blocking everything happens in order and a nonblocking we start events attaching callbacks and these
callbacks get fired later.
We're still printing out user wan and user to we're just doing it when the data comes back because the
data doesn't come back right away inside of no J as the event loop attaches a listener for the event
to finish.
In this case for that database to respond back when it does it calls the callback you pass in right
here and then we print it to the screen.
Now imagine this was a web server instead of the current example.
That would mean if a web server comes in looking to query the database we can't process other users
requests without spinning up a separate thread.
Now no genius is single threaded which means your application runs on one single thread.
But since we have non-blocking IO that's not a problem in a blocking context.
We could handle two requests on two separate threads.
But that doesn't really scale well because for each request we have to beef up the amount of CPQ and
ram resources that we're using for the application.
And this sucks because those threads they're still sitting idle just because we can spin up other threads
doesn't mean we should.
We're wasting resources that are doing nothing here instead of wasting resources by creating multiple
threads.
We're doing everything on one thread when a request comes in.
The IO is non-blocking.
So we're not taking up any more resources than we would be if it never happened at all.
Let's go ahead and run these examples in real time and see what we get.
And right here we have the two files that we saw over in the screen shot were going to be running both
of these files and I'm using the Adam editor to edit my text files.
These are things we're going to be setting up later in the section.
This is just for your viewing purpose.
You don't need to run these files so they're not provided.
Now the blocking and non-blocking files they're both going to get run and they're going to do similar
things obviously just in a different way.
Both use IO operations get users sync and get used to that take 5 seconds apiece.
The time is no different.
It's just the order they execute it that makes the non-blocking version much quicker.
Now to simulate and show how things work I'm going to add a few console dialog statements right here
starting user 1 starting user 2.
This is going to let us visualize how things work over inside of the terminal starting user to end starting.
User 1.
Perfect.
Once again as I promised this is never going to come up again where you're just watching me magically
create code.
For now though we're going to start by running the blocking file over in the terminal by running node
blocking J J.S. This is how we run files.
We type node and we specify the file name when I run the file we get some output starting at User 1
Prince to the screen and then it sits there.
Now we have the user 1 object printing to the screen with the name Andrew and starting user to Prince
to the screen.
After that the user two object comes back around five seconds later with a name of gen are two users
have printed to the screen and at the very end are some which is three prints to the screen.
Everything works great.
Notice that starting user one was immediately followed by the finishing of user 1 and starting user
2 was immediately followed by the finishing of user 2.
Because this is a blocking application.
Now we're going to run the nonblocking file which I called nonblocking.
Yes when I run this file starting user 1 prints starting user to print then some prints all back to
back around 5 seconds later at basically the same time user one and user to both print to the screen.
This is how nonblocking works just because we started an IO operation doesn't mean we can't do other
things like starting another one and printing some data to the screen.
In this case just a number.
This is the big difference and this is what makes nonblocking apps so fantastic.
They can do so many things at the exact same time without having to worry about the confusion of multi-threading
applications.
Let's go ahead and move back into the browser and take a look at the sentences again.
Knode uses an event driven non-blocking IO model that makes that lightweight and efficient.
And we just saw that in action because notas nonblocking we were able to cut down the time our application
took by half this non-blocking IO makes our apps super quick.
This is where the lightweight and efficient comes into play.
Now let's go to the last sentence node's package ecosystem NPM is the largest ecosystem of open source
libraries in the world.
This is what really makes Noad fantastic.
This is the cherry on top.
The community that people every day developing new libraries that solve common problems in your know
J.S. applications things like validating objects creating servers and serving up content live using
sockets.
There's libraries already built for all of those.
So you don't have to worry about this.
This means that you can focus on the specific things related to your application without having to create
all this infrastructure before you can even write real code code that does something specific to your
apps use.
Now NPM which is available over on NPM A-J Eskridge is the site we're going to be turning to for a lot
of third party modules if you're trying to solve a problem in node that sounds generic.
Chances are someone's already solved it.
For example if I want to validate some objects let's say I want to validate that a name property exists
and that there's an ID with a length of three.
I could go into Google or go into NPM.
I usually choose Google and I could google and PM validate object when I google that I'm just going
to look for results from NPM J ass dot com and here you can see the first three or so are from that
I can click the first one.
This is going to let me explore the documentation and see if it's right for me.
This one looks great so I can add it to my app without any effort.
Now we're going to be going through that process.
Don't worry I'm not going to leave you high and dry on how to add third party modules.
We're going to be using a ton of them in the course because this is what real no developers do.
They take advantage of the fantastic community of developers and that's the last thing that makes node
so great.
This is why node has come to the position of power that it currently sits at because it's nonblocking
meaning it's great for IO applications and it has a fantastic community of developers.
So if you ever want to get anything done there's a chance someone already wrote the code to do it.
This is not to say you should never use Rails or a python or any other blocking language again that
is not what I'm getting at.
What I'm really trying to show you is the power of no Jay ass and how you can make your applications
even better languages like Python have things like the library twisted which aims to add non-blocking
features to python though the big problem is all of the third party libraries those are still written
in a blocking fashion.
So you're really limited as to which libraries you can use since node was built nonblocking from the
ground up.
Every single library on NPM adjacent dot com is non-blocking.
So you don't have to worry about finding one that's non-blocking verse blocking.
You can install a module knowing it was built from the ground up using a non-blocking ideology.
That is it for this to video series looking deep into what node is and why it's so great in the next
couple of videos.
You're going to be writing your very first app and running it from the terminal.
So stay tuned.
I am super excited to show you how