In this video I want to take a quick moment to give you a tour of the various text editors you can use
for this course.
If you already have one you love using you can stop watching now because you can keep using the one
you have.
There's no need to switch editors to get anything done in this course.
Now if you don't have one and you're looking for a few options I always recommend using Adam which you
can find that Adam and I know it's free open source and it's available on all operating systems.
Linux OSX and Windows.
It's created by the folks behind get hub and it's the editor that I'm going to be using inside of this
course.
There's an awesome community of theme and plug in developers.
So you really can customize it to your liking.
Now aside from Adam there are a few other options.
I've heard a lot of people talking about Visual Studio code and they've been wondering why I don't use
in my courses I don't have any hands on experience with it but it does look pretty appealing at first
glance.
It is also open source free and it's available on all operating systems.
If you don't like Adam I highly recommend checking this out because I've heard so many good things via
word of mouth.
Next up we always have Sublime Text which you can find out sublime at text dot com.
Now Sublime Text is not free and it's not open source but it's a text editor that a lot of folks do
enjoy using.
I prefer Adam because it's very similar to sublime tax.
Though I find it snappier and easier to use.
Plus it's free and open source.
Now if you are looking for a more premium editor with all of the bells and whistles in ID as opposed
to a text editor I always recommend jet brains none of their products are free though they do come with
a 30 day free trial but they really are the best tools of the trade.
Do you find yourself in a corporate setting or you're out of a job where the company is willing to pay
for a editor.
I always recommend going with Jepp Raines all of their editors come with all of the tools you'd expect
like version control integration debugging tools and deploying tools built in.
Now it's definitely overkill for this course but I wanted to make you aware that they exist so down
the line you always have that choice.
As I said before in this course I'm going to be using atom.
I highly recommend it.
It has everything we need to create node apps.
So take a moment download the one you want to use.
Play around with it.
Make sure it fits your needs.
If not try another one.
When you're happy with one you can move on to the next video where we're going to create our very first
node application.
A really simple hello world example.
So stay tuned.
I will see you next time.