In this video you are going to be creating and running your very first node app while it will be a simple
one it's going to demonstrate the entire process from creating files to running them from the terminal.
The first step is going to be to create a folder.
Every project we create is going to live inside of its own folder.
I'm going to open up the finder on OSX and navigate to my desktop.
What I'd like you to do is open up the desktop on your OS whether you're on Linux or Windows or OSX
and create a brand new folder called Hello world.
Now I'm using capitalization on both the H and W..
You could also go with something like this.
Hello hyphen world.
Let's go ahead and use this option.
In a lower case i don't recommend using spaces in your project file or folder names as it only makes
it more confusing to navigate inside of the terminal.
Now we have this hello world folder and we can open it up inside of our editor.
Here I use command 0 to open up and I'm going to navigate to the desktop and a double click my hello
world folder on the left I have my files which are none.
Let's go ahead and create a new one.
I'm going to make a new file in the root of the project and we're going to call this one app dot J.
Yes this is going to be the only file we have inside of our node application.
And then here we can write some code that's going to get executed when we start the app in the future
we'll be doing crazy stuff like initializing databases and starting web servers.
But for now we're simply going to use cons. dialogue which means we're accessing the logged property
on the console object.
It's a function.
So we can call it with parentheses.
And we're going to pass in one argument a string Hello world.
I'm going to toss a semi-colon on the end and save the file.
This is going to be the first app we run.
Never remember there is a basic javascript requirement for this course so nothing here should look too
foreign to you.
I'll be covering everything new and fresh inside of this course but the basics.
Creating variables calling functions those should be something you're already familiar with.
Now that we have our out Jeff's file the only thing left to do is run it and we're going to do that
over in the terminal.
Now to run this program we have to navigate into our project folder.
If you're not familiar with the terminal I'll give you a quick refresher.
You can always figure out where you are using P.W. D on Linux or OSX or the dirty command on Windows
when you run it you're going to see something like this.
I'm in the Users folder and then I'm in my user folder and my user name happens to be Andrew.
When you open the terminal or the command prompt you're going to star in your user directory.
We can use C-D to navigate into the desktop.
And here we are.
Now we're sitting in the desktop.
The other command you can run from anywhere on your computer is forwards slash user's forwards slash
Andrew forward slash desktop.
This is going to navigate to your desktop no matter what folder you're located in the command up above
a CD desktop requires you to be in the user directory to work correctly.
Now that we're here though we can start by seeding into our project directory which we called Hello
hi hyphen world and once we're in here we can run in the ls command on Linux or Mac which is the dirk
command on windows to see all of our files.
And in this case we just have one we have app.
DOT.
J.S..
This is the file We're going to run.
Now before you do anything else make sure you see what I see here.
You should be in the hello world folder and you should have the app.
JS file inside.
If you do all we're going to do is run the node command followed by a space so we can pass in an argument
and that argument is going to be the file name app dot.
Yes once you have this in place you go ahead and hit enter and there we go hello world prints to the
screen and that is all it takes to create and run a very basic node application.
While our app doesn't do anything cool we're going to be using this process of creating folders files
and running them from the terminal throughout the course so it's a great start on our way to making
real world node apps.
That is it for this video and that is it for this section.
We took a look at what node is why it's cool and you created your very first application and the next
section we're going to dive in creating our first app.
I am super excited to start writing real world applications.
So stay tuned.
I will see you next time